MAYA:
So Finn, I’ve done as much as I can for our project on theatre
programmes.
How’s your research coming along?
FINN:
OK, Maya.
I didn’t know theatre programmes are called playbills in the USA till I started
looking into the topic.
FINN:
Even though I struggled to find many useful websites, I’m glad we picked this
subject.
No one else on the course is doing the same as us, although it
is one of the research areas of the module convenor.
MAYA:
That might actually put some people off.
FINN:
I suppose so.
Anyway, I hadn’t realised there are actually companies specialising in creating theatre programmes.
MAYA:
Yes, they’re quite common nowadays.
Contrary to what many people think, theatres don’t hire people to do the programmes,
in fact companies buy the rights to publish programmes on the theatre’s behalf –
and then make their money selling advertising space within the programme booklet.
FINN:
It must be easier for theatres to do it that way.
MAYA:
Yes.
FINN:
I remember reading something about programmes in early British theatre.
It said that the cast was always very important.
MAYA:
Yeah, audiences were very familiar with leading actors,
and big names would draw huge crowds.
FINN:
But I hadn’t realised that if the programme named a famous actor,
that’s who the public expected to perform.
FINN:
And if that didn’t happen, people accused the theatre of breaking their agreement with
the audience.
They would demand refunds,
and, if they didn’t get them, there were riots!
MAYA:
Outrageous.
That’d never happen now.
FINN:
No, people are too polite, even when they’re disappointed if the star of the
show misses a performance.
MAYA:
We should definitely include that information about early audiences in our project.
I also think it’s important to mention that lots of ordinary people at that
time were illiterate,
so theatre programmes were of limited value in advertising plays.
MAYA:
When a company of actors arrived in a town, they’d parade around the streets in their costumes, beating drums
and announcing their upcoming performances.
FINN:
Interesting.
I couldn’t imagine that happening now either.
MAYA:
There’s also an interesting comparison to make between eighteenth and nineteenth-century programmes.
FINN:
Wasn’t it in the nineteenth century that theatre programmes started to resemble programmes
today?
MAYA:
Yes.
And, unlike programmes from the eighteenth century, they always used colour.
FINN:
And there was a greater variety of designs.
But personally, I think eighteenth-century programmes were superior because they told the theatre-goers
so many things, including about the actors.
MAYA:
And about the writer, the plot,
and sometimes the history of the play.
FINN:
That’s right.
… What should we say about theatre programmes in the twentieth century?
MAYA:
I reckon the most important thing is the dramatic change they underwent during World
War Two.
FINN:
When the government imposed restrictions on the use of paper.
MAYA:
Yeah,
but that was only in the UK.
In the USA, programmes – or rather, playbills – continued to be published in
the same format …
FINN:
… while here in the UK, programmes became merely a single sheet of paper
folded to create four pages for text.
MAYA:
What I don’t really get is that, after the war, they didn’t go back
to being more than one sheet,
or change in any way for over twenty-five years.
MAYA:
I know there were paper shortages after the war,
but only for five or ten years.
FINN:
Strange.
MAYA:
I’ve got some pictures of programmes we could include on the slides for our
presentation.
FINN:
I found a couple too, Maya.
Let’s go through and see what we think.
MAYA:
Erm …, this is an old one, for a play called Ruy Blas.
FINN:
Never heard of that,
but the programme looks very decorative.
MAYA:
Good enough to put in a frame on the wall.
The images are just beautiful.
Finn, what did you find?
FINN:
I’ve got some pages from a programme for Man of La Mancha.
I thought this was a good programme to show, not because of the pictures,
but because it contains articles written by members of the theatre company.
FINN:
So we can learn how the production was created,
and the thoughts and feelings of the cast.
MAYA:
Good.
I’ve got a copy of a programme that’s now in a museum.
It’s for The Tragedy of Jane Shore and it’s said to be the earliest
surviving document to have been printed on Australia’s first printing press.
FINN:
Fantastic.
MAYA:
Another programme to talk about is for The Sailors’ Festival.
It comes from the British Library’s digitised collection of programmes that was started a
few years ago.
MAYA:
It already comprises over two hundred thousand programmes,
which is amazing.
FINN:
Wish I’d known about it while I was doing my research!